[music]
I am now
>> came back.
>> All right. Pizza. Good evening everyone.
Thank you for coming. We are going to
kick off the finance committee meeting
for March 9th. Starting with temporary
resolution 3226 that's coming through
public works. Mr. Carr.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. U Mr. Skover. Um
this is
the Arbor Valley Drive improvement
[snorts] project. Um we
um are putting this through to um accept
the funds from the city schools um the
$500,000 that the city schools is
contributing toward that and move the
other money around. But I will bring uh
[clears throat] Tim Deetsz up,
superintendent to go over this for us.
[clears throat]
>> Good evening.
Uh yeah, basically as John said, uh
[clears throat] we have to have
legislation so we accept the donation
from the schools, bring that into the
fund and then adjust several accounts
that Trish says we have to have to
adjust and make notifications of and
then uh reappropriate that money into
one of four places that are going to pay
for this project. Um so you'll see the
account numbers listed.
Um basically um
this is going to be a fastmoving
project. So um
and it require it's got a lot of moving
parts. So, um once once uh we get the
money where we need to moved, um I have
asked for two readings because come
April, I would like everything in place
so nothing holds up the progress once
construction starts because between the
time school lets out and then the new
school opens, everything on Arbor Valley
Drive needs to be done from roadway
improvements to bike trailments and
sidewalk installations and storm sewer
system installations,
striping the whole nine yards. And then
that same time frame, the schools have
to tear down the old building along with
the vocational building and get it off
site so they can do more of their work.
So the sooner the better we can get this
moving, I appreciate it.
>> Anybody have any questions?
>> I actually do. Tim, thank [snorts] you
so much for meeting or at least
answering my questions and then Kurt the
city engineer addressed some of my
concerns with this project.
>> And I do want to take the opportunity to
understand recognizing that you're
trying to create infrastructure
improvements and walkable enhancements
with limited funds in being creative and
knowing the time constraints. I do feel
like this is an opportunity that we need
to take a closer look at the pedestrian
safety and the students walking to and
from. We've we've talked about that.
>> Okay.
>> There's there's opportunity and and I
would really appreciate it if we could
take another look at that.
>> Great.
>> Thanks,
Cory.
>> Yes.
>> Do we have an idea what the total cost
is going to be?
>> Uh it's the bid came in at uh two just
over $2.6 6 million and uh in the
between that and the OP
the Ohio Public Works Commission grant
we're getting um they're they're going
to cover a small portion of that too. So
we could according to Jeff the engineer
assistant engineer it's going to be
anywhere between 2.6 and 2.8 million
total.
Hopefully less hopefully less when the
time comes they said they don't need
some pavement and we don't put that down
or they don't need this and we can take
it out. So there's some things that can
be non-performed but at this point we're
not sure what they are.
>> Any other questions? So this piece is
just accepting the city the city schools
money. So, I know it's we got a lot of
other
>> It's also making some new appropriations
into the proper expense line items.
>> I feel kind of lost because I am not on
public works anymore and I haven't seen
the um that's my fault for not coming to
the meeting, but I haven't seen Do you
have the
>> Do we have the full like layout and all
of the drawings and all of that stuff?
>> Uh the engineers have the full set of
plans. Yes.
>> Okay.
>> Have we seen
>> We can We can get those to you. I'm sure
they're
>> I'm just curious cuz uh and I'm certain
that the service safety director would
be super excited for me to not call
every football Friday night and be like,
"Hey, the parking's all
all jacked up and people are parking
where they're not supposed to.
>> This should fix that."
>> I know. I'm excited to see that. That's
why I was curious. So, all right. miss
your calls.
>> I'll still call you just so you know I'm
still around. [clears throat]
>> And just so you know, there is a
provision in that construction time
frame where access will be maintained on
the two Friday or two Saturday nights
for the festival concert. Um and
supposedly there's a football game in
there somewhere, too. So,
>> um we got a lot of things to work
around, but we'll get her done.
>> Right. Sounds good. Thank you. Any other
questions?
All right, Mr. Carr. I have two readings
and Miley is your second.
>> That's correct.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Temporary resolution 3326.
That's actually coming through safety,
not service as it is on the agenda. Mr.
Bisjack.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. Chair. Uh once again,
this legislation comes from the fire
department. Uh this legislation is
seeking to um accomplish uh essentially
an allowance, a retroactive allowance if
you will, the fire department applying
for the uh US Department of
Transportation's [laughter]
build program. Uh there's a grant that
they have in the amount of $800,000.
this this funding, should the city be
fortunate enough to receive it, uh from
the Department of Transportation, uh
will actually allow the fire department
to install various um devices on traffic
poles so that when you know an ambulance
or fire trucks going through the city,
um it can actually trigger all the
lights to turn red, stop the entire
intersection, and essentially allow uh
the fire truck to or the ambulance to
proceed as quickly as possible to where
they need to get and help our residents.
Uh so once again due to the fact that
this application was made earlier in in
uh in February uh I'm going to be
requesting suspension uh just because of
that timeline. I'm seeking to do this in
one read and you Mr. Skoonover will be
my second.
>> Okay.
Does anyone have any questions? I see
the chief standing back there. Chief,
did you want to add anything?
>> I I had one more thing to add, Mr.
Chair. Sorry, there is no local match to
this. This is purely funding from the
federal government. Sorry, I wanted to
throw that nugget out there, too. Thank
you. Okay,
>> that was a great summary. I'm just here
if anybody has any questions.
>> Okay, any questions for the chief?
>> I do have a question, Mr. Chair.
>> Yes.
>> Um Chief,
>> yes, sir.
>> I My question is um this this
legislation is authorizing the
department to apply for the grant, but
it correct me if I'm wrong, but you've
the department's already applied for it.
Is that correct?
>> That is correct.
>> Okay. If if the my question is if if the
department's already applied, why why do
we need to rush this along if the
process has already begun?
>> Please go ahead.
>> Can I address that, Mr. Chairman?
>> Yeah.
>> Um, [clears throat]
so basically the language included in
section one allows you to ratify action
that was already taken by city council.
Um but we would prefer obviously that
you get the uh the abil you get the
authorization rather than the
forgiveness of city council after the
fact. Um and depending on the grant um
he may need to supply typically you do
need to supply your authorization. I
know I have to um from city council and
so the sooner you can get that in um the
more likely you are to meet all the
pre-grant award conditions and therefore
be considered for the actual funding. um
they'll just knock you out of the
process if you're not. And so that's why
we put it on an accelerated timeline.
>> Understood. Thank you. That's very
helpful. Thank you,
>> Mr. Cohen.
>> Will this 800,000 cover the entire cost
of the system that you're going to put
in
>> as far as you know?
>> Yeah, the the budget for the grant um
would be for 100% of the costs. um that
is to put this the equipment in all our
frontline u first responder vehicles um
for the fire department and um for this
grant seeing the value in it. We also
included all the police cruisers um and
also all the all the different equipment
that would go in the traffic um boxes as
Councilman Bisjack alluded to. Um it is
a reimbursement grant. So we would be
reimbursed 100% of the expenses um due
to some um unique characteristics of the
city of Langster census tracks and how
we are eligible for the grant.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other questions?
>> Great. All right. Thank you, Chief.
>> All right. So, you're going to be asking
for suspension on that one this evening?
>> Yes, Mr. Chair.
>> All right. Temporary resolution 3426
that's coming through finance. Uh that
is me and I will kick it over to Miss
Woody.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Uh similar to
the fire grant, this is a grant that we
just stumbled upon uh the day of our
last meeting and we didn't have time to
get legislation in. Um it's a 10,000
grant, a $10,000 grant through AARP. And
the idea for this grant came from our
city planner uh Chasyn Carter and our
community development director Michelle
McCrady who had been meeting with uh if
you're familiar with the agency down the
street soil the center for independent
living uh one of their members was
trying to get into a local downtown
business but because there was no ADA
ramp they could not actually shop in the
local business and so when we found this
AP grant uh we thought it would be great
to apply for portable portable ramps to
supply for our downtown businesses, but
really any business in the city that
would need to use a portable ramp, we
would be willing to help circulate
those. Um, so similar to the fire
department, the grant was already due
last week. So I talked to finance chair
uh Skunover and asked if we could please
submit the grant for 10,000 to get these
portable ramps and then ratify it this
evening. And then uh like law director
Hall said, we will send this resolution
uh to the ARP grant award or the grant
reviewers so that they see that this was
approved by city council.
>> Perfect. Any questions on that one?
>> I do have a question. Yes, Mr. Chair.
>> Um so once once this uh let's say we're
awarded the $10,000 grant and the ramps
are purchased, who who then owns the
ramps? Does the city own the ramps or do
the private businesses own the ramps?
>> The city will own the ramps. Our plan is
to work with our DDL and SID uh uh
director who's in our front row to help
us communicate with the local business
owners um so that they know that these
ramps are available to use.
>> Okay. Thank you. Followup, Mr. Chair.
>> Yes. Um I I'm my only concern is I think
that if you know if the businesses
themselves are having trouble with um
ADA compliance and stuff like that, I
believe the businesses themselves should
be the ones to front the cost of the
ramps. So I'm a little concerned about
this. Um but um I know that's not really
a question, but more of a comment. So
thank you, Mr. Chair.
>> Thank you. Any other questions?
All right. We will be asking for
suspension on that one this evening as
well. Temporary resolution 3526 that's
coming through public works. Mr. Carr,
thank you. Um, this legislation is to
readvertise for bids for the 6th Avenue
Bridge project as we only received one
bid on that and it was more than 20%
over the original $2.4 million estimate.
Um, I'll ask I can ask uh city engineer
Kurt Shank to come up if there's any
questions on this.
[snorts]
>> All right. Good evening. Yeah. So, we
advertised as uh John said and the bid
came in over just over 20% higher than
the engineers estimate which means we
have to rebid it. Um, we didn't see any
errors with the bid. It's just that
across the board the prices were a
little bit higher than what our engineer
prime engineering had anticipated.
Um, so we're trying to get out to bid
quickly, as quick as we can because the
later in the year it gets, the the
higher the bids are going to be. That's
usually how it works. Um, so we're
scrambling to get this resolution in so
that we can um essentially raise the
estimate. I think it's 2 2.55
million. We went through and adjusted
that estimate. Our hope is that a lot of
times the biders will withhold their
bids if they know it's not going to be
re awarded. They don't want to show
their cards. So, we're hoping by
increasing the estimate, we'll actually
get more competitive bids and maybe get
a better bid than we got the first time
around. Um, we like to stay optimistic
when we can. So, but we really need to
get the project done this year. We
didn't want to put off the project, so
we think this is our uh our best next
step for this.
>> I have a question. Um, so for the 2.55
million, does that include the inspector
cost or is that an addition?
>> That's the con. That's the uh
construction cost.
>> Just the construction cost, not the
inspection as well. So, that'll be
additional funds. Okay.
Any
other questions for Kurt?
>> And this can go full three readings and
Mr. Bisjack will be my second.
>> Okay.
Thank you. Temporary resolution 3626
that's coming through finance. That is
another grant request from service
safety director.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chairman. This grant is
for the state capital budget and we've
received um the eligible project list uh
right after our last council meeting.
The grant is actually due this Thursday.
So the mayor and I met with our parks
director, which parks really was the
only thing that we would have eligible
on the list. Um, so we met with the park
superintendent on Friday uh to go
through some of the projects for the
parks. What we decided on was the rising
shelter at Rising Park. Uh, it needs
restoration. It's in pretty bad shape
right now. Uh, the cost is going to be
500,000.
That would cover the cost of the
project. There would be no local funds
involved with that. Um, and I know Mr.
Gatefield could not be here tonight to
speak on this. Uh, but I will try to
answer any questions that you have
regarding the project. Again,
we do not like to ask for suspension. We
would much rather have three readings,
but unfortunately with these grants,
when we find a chance, uh we want to
grab that chance when we can. Uh so, we
are asking for suspension, we understand
it's a short turnaround, but if we don't
apply, then we don't have a chance at
getting the funds, and $500,000 to me is
worth asking for suspension.
questions.
>> I have a question, Mr. Chair.
>> Yes.
>> Um, service safety director Woody. Um,
well, do you anticipate uh because I I
I've seen these how these capital
budgets work. Sometimes you ask for a
certain amount, but the legislature only
gives you a fraction potentially. Um, do
you see this project going forward even
if we are not awarded the full 500,000
for the project? I would say if we are
not awarded the whole $500,000 for the
project, it would come back to the
council committee and the park board to
discuss if there are any other funds for
it. I so I don't want to speak on behalf
of Superintendent Gayfield. I don't know
that he would have other funds for it,
which is why we applied for this grant.
So without him here, my gut says no, we
would not move forward unless
he knows of other funds that I'm not
aware of. But that's why we chose this
project because there were no other
funds available for this project.
>> Understood. Thank you.
>> Any other questions?
>> Seeing none, ask for suspension uh in
the regular meeting with Mr. Als is my
second
temporary resolution 3726.
And yet again another grant application.
Miss Woody,
>> third time's a charm. Uh this is another
capital grant. This is through Congress
Congressman Balderson and we are looking
at applying for a waterline project. So
originally this is what we were hoping
to do in state capital budget but it
wasn't an eligible project under state
capital budget. Timing's everything. We
found out uh just last week that we
could apply for this capital budget
budget um through the federal
government. This is a project that was
identified actually back when Mayor
Sheffller was still mayor and Paul
Martin was service safety director. They
were looking for funds to fund this
project. It really completes the water
line uh heading northeast on 188 toward
Pleasantville. We have a line that we
were trying to loop around. Um so it
would complete that waterline project
that has been on our plans for 15 to 20
years. Um, but in addition to that, it
would also allow the county to tie into
our services, Pleasant Township Fire
Department and Lancaster City Schools.
So, this is a project, again, we've been
looking for funding since Mayor and I
both took our positions with the city.
Um, so this is an eligible project under
uh Congressman Balderson's capital
budget. So, we are hoping to apply for
this grant if you are able to and
willing to authorize this uh legislation
this evening.
>> Um, is there a match for this?
>> There is not a match. And if we did not
get the funding for this 100% the
project will not go because we have no
other money to do this project. That's
why we've been looking for grant funds
for I think it's been at least four
years that they've been looking for
funds for this project. even with
working with the other entities not
coming up.
>> Correct. Interesting.
>> It's it's over $4 million. So even
working with the other entities uh we
just there's no way for us to fund that
without this grant.
>> If I could, the other entities have
indicated that they they will contribute
some share of the funds, but the the
project's a city project. Uh looping
that looping of the line or connecting
of the line uh is one of our long-term
goals. So they will benefit from it, but
it's primarily to uh finish one of our
important projects to have water coming
from two directions in the city. So if
you have water line out in one
direction, you can feed water from the
other [clears throat] direction.
Any other questions?
Seeing none, we'll ask for suspension.
Mr. Als would be my second on that one
as well.
I'm not aware of any other resolutions
that are not on the agenda. So, new
ordinances, temporary ordinance 526 that
is coming through finance
um law director Hall, would you like to
speak to that?
>> Yes, sir. Thank you. So, as I informed
law committee um at our last uh
regularly scheduled meeting, one of my
assistant prosecutors has enough time in
opers now that he can essentially
retire. Um he's fairly young, so he
doesn't intend to retire retire. He
intends to be semi-retired. Uh which is
fortunate because um right after he
informed me he was going to retire in
February, uh one of my other assistant
prosecutors informed me that he would be
out um on FMLA um for a significant
period of time. And so we're running
three courtrooms at any given time. Um
and that only gives us two assistant
prosecutors left to run those three
courtrooms. Um but because uh the one
assistant prosecutor is semi-retiring,
he agreed to wait to push his um his
date to leave back until June uh so that
he can train whoever comes in and
hopefully takes that position and stays
there long term. So the February bar was
given um the last week of February. The
results come in at the end of April. Um
most likely we will get a new uh a newly
licensed attorney. um we don't typically
get uh folks that are, you know, more
experienced or have a lot of
prosecutorial experience just based on
the fact that, you know, what we're
paying is more uh appropriate for
somebody at the beginning stages of
their career. Um but because the one
assistant prosecutor has been here
longer, the goal is to hire somebody in
temporarily so that he can help train
that individual before he leaves. um and
his salary is significantly higher than
the salary of the new person coming in.
So the goal is to not spend any
additional money um because we will be
saving some money um when he leaves the
office in June. So I asked for a uh a
bump to four assistant prosecutors just
for a brief window of time so that we
can hire and train somebody and get them
up and running um before my one
assistant prosecutor is off on FMLA and
the other one has retired. So that's the
reason for that and I'm happy to answer
any questions anybody might have.
>> Any questions?
>> Thank you.
>> Pretty straightforward after your
explanation. I like it. Thanks.
Okay.
Tempor um that's going to be the three
readings is fine on that one. Yes. Okay.
And Mr. Sullie is my second. All right.
Temporary ordinance 626. That's coming
through law committee. Uh Mr. car is
gonna introduce that one this evening.
>> Okay. This is a lease amendment to the
property that Park National Bank sits on
on Memorial Drive. And given that I just
I have read through this, but given that
I'm the just became the first on this,
I'm going to defer to law director uh
Hall to give us some background on this.
>> Sure. Absolutely. So, um, back in 2001,
uh, the city had property at the
intersection of Edgewood Avenue and
Memorial Drive. If you recall, it's a
little triangle, um, right there across
from McDonald's where the Park National
Bank sits. Um, the bulk of their parking
lot and where the ATM is located is
actually city property. It was canal
land that was given back to the city
from the state when they abandoned the
canals. So, it was free property for the
city, but the city, knowing that it had
value on Memorial Drive, chose to bid it
out for lease. Um, it was bid out for
lease. A lease was executed in 2001 with
the owner of Roots at the time, as well
as Park National, Fairfield National
Bank. I apologize. Um, since then,
they've obviously become Park National
Bank and Roots has gone away. The lease
was amended once in 2011 to reflect a
longer period. Um, originally the lease
didn't have a fixed term and park, it's
my understanding because I was not doing
this then that Park National Bank wanted
a fixed lease so that they would have
um, you know, they were making
improvements on the property, the ATM
specifically. They didn't want the the
lease to end in the next three years and
then them to have to rip that ATM and
all of the improvements that they were
putting in on the the property out. Um
and so the city agreed to do that
because there were some other benefits
um to the city for doing that. Well, now
um since then we have learned that the
process for readjusting the lease for
rent escalation uh it doesn't work as
smoothly or as well as we would like. So
every 5 years the service safety
director is required to hire an
appraiser to do an appraisal of the
property. And unfortunately um it's not
a cheap process and you know, our
service safety directors, I think they
come and go um occasionally. And so, you
know, it would be better if there was a
process that was continuous and allowed
for adjustment continuously rather than
once every five years. And the service
safety director has to remember to pay
an appraiser to do that. Uh, also the
issue for Park is, um, they're now
required to take the entire fixed term
and consider it a liability on their
balance sheet. And because there's 87
years left of the fixed term that was
set, um, that results in millions of
dollars, which is a a change, obviously,
a significant change to their balance
sheet. So um in exchange for giving them
a shorter set term which will be an
initial term of four years and then
five-year automatic renewals after that
for 50 years that's up to 2076
whereas the original lease was supposed
or the the second amendment rather to
the lease um was supposed to go to
21108.
Um but they were satisfied with the term
of 50 years. Um, and then it'll also
allow us to do a rent escalation based
on CPI, which is what we typically do.
The consumer price index, um, annually
for all Midwest, um, whatever the
increase is, that's what we use unless
it's below 3%. We have a 3% floor, um,
that we use, and they were they were
more than happy to agree to those terms.
So, the mayor and I have talked about
this previously. Um, the service safety
director and I talked about this.
everybody was in agreement um that it's
probably best for all concerned to just
go ahead and amend the lease for the
second time um in order to add those
make those changes um and fix it make it
a little better for everybody involved.
Anybody have any questions?
I see none. Thank you very much.
>> Yep.
So, we're going to do three readings on
that one.
>> Three readings and Mr. frog will be my
second.
>> Okay.
>> All right. I don't have any other
ordinances on the agenda. I wasn't made
aware of any when we came in. So, moving
on to department updates. Do we have
anybody here for department updates?
Miss Bosco
City at 6:30? But so, um last year Ohio
Department of Development created a new
uh a new program for housing. It's
called REDD,
Residential Economic Development
District. And um what it was was
incentivizing developments that are near
mega projects um to create workforce
housing. And when they say workforce, it
has nothing to do with what uh houses
would be uh for sale, what the cost of
houses that are for sale or the lease
rates of units. what it is is to create
housing in communities that are going to
be um heavily affected by mega projects.
So, um we um and I don't know if you
guys know, I didn't know till I read um
till I checked out the map, we are
within 20 miles of four mega projects.
And
um I'm going to forget the mall. uh am
uh Amazon in Etna uh or Amazon in
Pascala, the solar panel manufacturer in
Etna and the Millerport Vantage data
data center site. So four very big
projects. Um over actually in January I
applied with three different developers.
So, we applied um three different
applications and we just found out that
the Casto project on Sheridan was
awarded a million dollars to go toward
that development. And it's pretty
amazing. This is um $10 million program.
Um they have now uh divvied it all up in
the first application process. So, we
won't have another try for another year.
They're going to put 15 million in that.
Five projects were um awarded and
Lancaster is the only one in central
Ohio and it's just it I it came as a
huge surprise that we actually got it. I
remember quite a few times in the
process of going through it thinking why
are we even doing this? We'll never get
this. But um but we were able to do
that. Um and and like I said we had
three developers that had reached out
and wanted to um apply for for this
grant. So a million dollars out of you
know onetenth of the program is coming
to Lancaster. So just wanted to share
that with everybody.
>> Fantastic. Thanks.
[clears throat]
Anyone else for department updates?
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> I really don't want to have to follow
that because that's such great news, but
congratulations Stephanie and good work.
Um my update is that we have a blood
drive tomorrow at city hall. And so if
you have not scheduled time to come and
give your blood, uh we are looking for
people to help. We are down in our
appointments this time and the need is
real. So if you are available tomorrow
between 8:30 a.m. and 2 p.m. I would
invite you council as a whole to come
and donate blood as well as members of
the audience and our public who may be
home watching. All are welcome tomorrow
between 8:30 and 2 at city hall on the
second floor.
>> Great. Thank you.
>> I'm going to be taking a nap from
Chick-fil-A [laughter]
visit, so maybe maybe not.
>> You could go before.
>> Fair enough. I'll go before. What?
>> Well, you got invited. That's nice.
>> Oh, that's [clears throat] right. I'm
sorry.
Any
[clears throat] other department updates
besides Mr. Als didn't get invited
yesterday or for tomorrow?
>> It's not the only one.
>> I know [clears throat]
you think it's big enough. It would be
okay.
>> There are three open spots for the
Chick-fil-A event tomorrow.
>> And I Larry's name is actually on all
three.
>> Now Larry has to go.
>> These are not These are just This is
folks that can't attend. I actually
can't attend. I have our um port board
meeting um and Stephanie's going to be
with me as well, but um but I I truly I
have three spots available and I'd love
to make sure those are filled.
>> Thank you. Anyone else for department
updates? Seeing none, we're moving on to
meeting prep.
Yes, this evening we had on the agenda
an update from um parks, but that is um
regarding the trees, but that's actually
next month because it's Arbor Day. So,
please disregard that on your agenda.
Any other discussion items for finance?
Seeing none,
entertain a motion to adjurnn.
>> So moved.
>> I will second that. and we are adjourned
at 6:32.
>> The regular regular meeting of Lancaster
City Council will commence at 6:40.
The Frankie Smith [music] Funeral Home
and Crematory in Lancaster and the
Johnson Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore
have a long and wonderful history of
[music] serving our community. Feel free
to give us a call at 74-653652.
Stop in [music] and see us at either of
our two locations, 405 North Columbus
Street in Lancaster and 207 South Main
Street in Baltimore. Respect for
tradition, [music] regard for change.
Great [music] automotive service is just
around the corner at the Buckeye family
of dealerships. Whether it's Buckeye
Nissan at Hillyard, Georgeesville
[music]
Nissan at the Georgeesville Auto Mall,
Buckeye Honda of Lancaster, Buckeye
Toyota of Lancaster, or Buckeye [music]
Collision Center in Hillyard. Team
Buckeye services all makes and models at
each location, utilizing modern
practices with hundreds of years of
experience, giving you peace of mind.
That's how we Buckeye.
Join me in a moment of silence for 7
service members who were killed in Iran.
Please join me in the pledge of
allegiance
to the flag of the United States of
America and to the republic for it
stands one nation
indivisible with liberty and justice for
all.
I call the March 9th, 2026 Lancaster
City Council meeting to order.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als here,
>> Mr. Bisjack
>> here.
>> Mr. Carr
>> Miss Cohen
>> here.
>> Mrs. Hoop
>> here. Mr. Nisley
>> here.
>> Mr. Skunover
>> And Miss Smiley
>> here.
>> Let the record reflect that eight
members of Lancaster City Council are
present.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
we excuse Mr. Sie and Mr. OG.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to excuse
Mr. Sullie and Mr. OG. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign.
>> Now move to reading and disposing of the
journal.
>> I have regular meeting minutes dated
February 23rd, [snorts] 2026.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to receive
and file the journal. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign.
>> Reports of city officials.
>> I have five of them. I have email dated
February 12th, 2026 regarding March 12th
planning commission meeting submitted by
city planner Chasing Carter. Email dated
February 23rd, 2026 regarding public
records request on Hawking Township.
Submitted by law director Stephanie
Hall. Email dated February 25th, 2026
regarding 2025 Lancaster Fire Department
annual report submitted by Fire Chief
Slade Schultz. Series of emails dated
March 3rd, 2026 regarding legislative
process submitted by President Jeff
Porter and law director Stephanie Hall.
And then email dated March 5th, 2026
regarding flooding near the west side of
Lancaster, submitted by environmental
engineer Denise Cruz.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to receive
and file the reports of city officials.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign.
>> Now move to communications.
>> I have two this evening. I have email
dated March 4th, 2026 regarding proposed
zoning language for data centers
submitted by Meg Fr. and then mail dated
March 5th, 2026 regarding liquor license
for 1454 Warehouse, Inc. submitted by
the Ohio Department of Commerce,
Division of Liquor Control.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the communications.
>> Second. We
>> have a motion and second to receive and
file the communications. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign.
>> We have no special presentation or
awards this evening. Uh we have no
petitions or memorials. We have now
reached the time in our meeting uh for
permission of voters and taxpayers to
address council. Are there any
individuals present this evening that
would like to address council? If you
would like to address council, please
approach the podium. Please sign with
your name and address and please state
that for the record. Comments are
limited to three minutes and um you must
be addressing council, not asking
questions of the audience.
>> All righty. Lancaster City Council.
Thank you for having me tonight. I
appreciate it. Um, please excuse me. I'm
a little anxious right now. My name is
Daniel Delignore Jr. I reside at 1035
Sugar Grove Road Southeast here in
Lancaster. And I am um speaking tonight
to ask you guys to please lift the
moratorium against cannabis here in the
uh city of Lancaster. Lancaster is
losing money as we speak. Currently um
every 3 to 5 minutes uh the Lancasterian
spends $200 in a different city on
cannabis. Um, additionally, that tax
money can be used on government
buildings, schools, and other public
buildings to improve the quality of our
community. Additionally, Ohio is
covering from the nationwide opioid
epidemic. Scientific studies show that
use that people use cannabis to decrease
opioid and other prescription drug usage
as well as alcohol usage. Um, these
studies are published in PubMed, JAMAMA,
and other peer-reviewed um, scientific
online uh, journals that you can read
and and see for yourself. Placing a
moratorium on something that 2.2 million
Ohioans already voted on does nothing
but take harm reduction out of the hands
of Ohioans and puts it in the hands of
the very entities that heavily
contribute to the opioid epidemic.
Additionally, it shows your constituents
and the farmers of Fairfield County that
you do not care about their will. This
is um hypocritical as there are liquor
stores in abundance on every almost
every street corner in Lancaster.
Additionally, alcohol kills 178,000
Americans yearly and 2.2 2 million
people worldwide. According to the CDC
and DEA, cannabis has killed zero people
due to an overdose.
I think society would agree that it's
time to stop demonizing a non-lethal
plant. If we're so concerned about the
children, there would be age
restrictions on beverages like Alani,
Monster energy drinks, Red Bull, and
charge lemonades sold down the road of
Panera that were putting people in their
graves a few years ago. Um, this isn't
heard of with natural cannabis. again.
Um, please, city council, let's focus on
education, regulation, and the non-
monopolization of Ohio of the Ohio
cannabis market. Let's build a future
that chooses harm reduction over stigma.
Let's be a shining example and show Ohio
that their opinions and minds can
change. Let me remind you, 52% voted yes
on issue two. 52% of Lancasterians. That
is a majority of Lancasterians who voted
yes on on cannabis legalization in 2023.
Also,
um let's please stop banning things or
putting public memoriams in place,
moratoriums in place on things we don't
understand as that creates more interest
and intrigue by young adolescents, which
is what we're trying to prevent in the
first place. I think that if we set up
or work towards setting up a regulated
cannabis market in this area of the
state, we can really be a shining
example of what education, regulation,
and listening to the will of your
constituents looks like.
Additionally,
um, studies show that in areas where
cannabis use isn't banned, teen usage
goes down due to much of the elimination
of the black market. Teens are not going
to dis to the black market to get it
anymore because they're being educated
on responsible use.
>> You've reached your three minutes, if
you could please conclude.
>> Yep. 100%. So, I want to end by saying I
pray that the city council is able to
change their minds on this. I am
somebody who um has personally my life
has been saved um by cannabis.
[clears throat] I used to be addicted to
alcohol and benzoazipines
since using cannabis. I have been able
to graduate college, hold down multiple
corporate jobs and I work multiple jobs
currently. I door dash. I also have
worked um a busing job and a greeter job
at Elorado Sod Downs and I am also an
employee of Cardinal Health. So,
>> thank you sir. Are there any other
individuals who'd like to address city
council this evening?
>> [clears throat]
>> Good evening, council. My name is Brian
Everett and I'm speaking today regarding
both the design of streets in our city
in general and specifically with respect
to the upcoming changes to Arbor Valley
Drive. The proposed construction on
Arbor Valley Drive must contain physical
traffic calming measures. To not include
such simple elements on a street that
combines inexperienced drivers, student
pedestrians, and high volume traffic
during dusk and dark hours is a recipe
for disaster. As a schoolboard member, I
feel frequent communications from
community members and parents and a
repeat concern expressed to me as
concern over safe routes to school,
specifically the speed of drivers on
Arbor Valley Drive, which frequently
results in near misses and loss of
control of cars. Making the street wider
and smoother will only make it more
dangerous and god forbid, more deadly.
There has been discussion of painting uh
the impediment of parked cars or law
enforcement presence as methods to
control speed on the street. I would say
paint is not infrastructure. Similar on
the non-smoking areas of restaurants in
days past, absent physical
infrastructure, pain is just wishful
thinking, and a car going even 20 or 30
miles an hour can easily travel from the
street to the bike path in the blink of
an eye. Vehicles will only be parked
along the street in a limited number of
days and times, and not when students
are traveling to or from the school in
the dark. I don't even believe we need
the widening and the additional parking.
The new parking lot at the school will
add 281 spaces already. Finally, at
nearly every city council meeting I
attend, there's a discussion of the
staffing and budget for our safety
services. Building a street that
requires the presence of law enforcement
to be considered safe is not only
lacking in design, but setting up the
city for an avoidable ongoing expense.
The old adage that speed kills applies
here. At 20 mph, nine out of 10
pedestrians struck by a vehicle will
survive. At 30 miles an hour, five out
of 10 pedestrians struck by a vehicle
will survive. And at 40 mph, only one
out of 10 pedestrians struck by a
vehicle will survive. Our Valley Drive
needs physical traffic calming measures.
Bumpouts, raised crosswalks, speed
humps, chicanees. There's a wide variety
of lowcost measures that can be directly
incorporated into this project and
prevent injury or death to our
community's children. I strongly
encourage the city to avail themselves
of the many resources available
regarding best practices for designing
complete streets that serve all
community members and save money and
lives. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir. Are there any other
individuals who wish to address council
this evening?
Seeing none, we thank you for coming.
Reports of standing committees.
>> I have six this evening. I have law
committee meeting minutes dated February
24th, 2026 submitted by Miss Smiley.
Service committee meeting minutes dated
February 23rd, 2026 submitted by Mr.
Nisley. Water water pollution meeting
minutes dated March 2nd, 2026, submitted
by Mr. Als. Finance committee meeting
agenda dated March 6, 2026, submitted by
Mr. Skunover. Finance committee meeting
minutes dated March 6, 2026, submitted
by Mr. Skunover. and public works
committee meeting schedule or I'm sorry,
minutes um dated March 9th, 2026
submitted by Mr. Carr.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to receive
and file reports of standing committees.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Reports of
special committees.
>> There are no reports this evening.
>> We have no public hearing. So we will
move on to the reading of resolutions
beginning with the third reading of
temporary resolution 2620 or 2326.
>> A resolution to increase receipts
appropriate from the unencumbered
balance. Amend the certificate with the
county auditor in the 045 police and
fire levy fund 2047
for CPT state grant reimbursement. This
is through safety committee. Mr. Bisjack
and Mr. Skunover.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you Mr. President. And I move that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
23-26.
>> Second.
>> A motion second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 2326. Any discussion? Council
member Pisch.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. President. Once again,
I just would like to remind council that
this is uh a piece of legis legislation
seeking to accept reimbursement in the
amount of about $95,225
from the Ohio Attorney General's office.
Once again, there's a two-year delay to
this. Um, but these funds can also be
used to help offset some CPT training
that our current police department
utilizes as well. So, that's all I have
to say, Mr. President. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr, [clears throat]
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Miss Smiley,
>> yes. Temporary resolution 2326
passes 8 to zero. We now move on to the
second reading of resolutions beginning
with temporary resolution 2526.
>> A resolution to authorize all actions
necessary to accept a northeast Ohio
public energy council to 2026 energized
community grant. Three finance committee
Mr. Skunover and Mr. Als
>> council member Skunover.
>> Second of three readings please. Second
of three readings on temporary
resolution 2526.
Temporary resolution 2726.
>> A resolution to increase and decrease
appropriations in the water revenue fund
6003 to cover a shortfall in the
retirement benefits account. This is
through water water pollution control
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This will be
the second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 2726.
Temporary resolution 26 or excuse me
2826.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to enter into a contract
for the construction of Frederick Street
sewer separation project. This is again
through water water pollution control
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Miss Cohen.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This will
stand as the second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 2826.
Temporary resolution 3026. a resolution
to authorize a then announced
certificate for payment of an AE
electric bill for the street lighting in
the general fund 10001 and to declare an
emergency. This through finance
committee, Mr. Skunover and Mr. Als.
>> Council member Spoonover.
>> Yes, Mr. President. I'd like to make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the third reading of temporary
resolution 3026.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary resolution 3026.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> I don't have any. Thank you. Please call
the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> And Miss Smiley,
>> Motion to suspend passes 8 to zero. Uh,
Council Member Skunover.
>> Yes. Mr. Mr. President, I'd like to make
a motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon written record at temporary
resolution 3026.
>> Second motion a second to pass and gross
and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 3026. Any
discussion, council member?
>> I do not.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Coop,
>> yes. Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skoover,
>> yes. and Miss Smiley.
>> Yes.
>> Temporary resolution 3026 passes 8 to
zero. Move to temporary resolution 3126,
>> a resolution to increase and decrease
appropriations in the general fund 10001
to cover a uniform allowance for a
recent promotion within the Lancaster
Fire Department and to declare an
emergency. This is through safety
committee. Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Al.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. This will
stand as the second of three readings.
Second of three readings on temporary
resolution 3126.
We'll now move to first readings
beginning with temporary resolution
3226.
>> A resolution to increase receipts
appropriate from the unencumbered
balance. Amend the certificate with the
county auditor and the LDOT improvement
fund 3014
to amend the certificate of
appropriations and appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and the general
improvement fund at 3016 and the three
Mill street levy improvement improvement
levy fund 20009 for funding of the Arbor
Valley Drive Improvement Program and to
declare an emergency. This through
public works committee Mr. Carr and Miss
Smiley.
>> Council member Carr. Um nothing to add
other than what was prevent presented in
finance. Um this we will go two readings
on this and move for suspension next
meeting.
>> So first of two
>> first of two readings. Thank you very
much. First of two readings on temporary
resolution 3226.
Temporary resolution 3326. A resolution
authorizing the Lancaster Fire
Department to apply for the butter
utilizing investments to leverage
development grant program through the US
Department of Transportation and to
declare an emergency. This is through
service committee.
>> Nope, I apologize. Through safety
committee, Mr. Bisjack and Mr. Skuniver.
>> Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council suspend its rules and wave the
second and third reading for temporary
resolution 33-26.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
suspend the rules and wave the second
and third reading of temporary
resolution 3326.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> Uh just repeating what I said in the
finance committee which was once again
due to the type timeline that we need to
have all this paperwork in by. Uh that's
why I'm asking for suspension.
>> That's all. Thank you, Mr. President.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes. Mr. Nisley,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> And Miss Smiley,
>> yes.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third reading of temporary
resolution 3326. It passes 8 to zero.
Council member Bisjack.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record temporary resolution
33-26.
>> Second.
>> A motion is second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 3326. Any further discussion?
>> Nothing further from finance. Thank you,
Mr. President. Thank you. Um, from
safety.
>> Well, when I talked about finance, I
have nothing further to add than what I
discussed in finance.
>> Thank you.
>> Sorry.
>> All right. No problem. Um, please call
the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> And Miss Smiley,
>> Motion to pass. Temporary resolution
3326 passes 80. Temporary resolution
3426,
>> a resolution to authorize the service
safety director to apply for the 2026
AARP community challenge grant program
and to declare an emergency. This is
through finance committee, Mr. Skunover
and Mr. Als.
>> Council member Spoonover.
>> Yes, Mr. President. I'd like to make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third readings
of temporary resolution 3426.
>> Second. We have a motion in a second to
suspend the rules and we have the second
and third reading of temporary
resolution 3426. Any discussion? Council
member Skunover.
>> We discussed during finance. This is
just to
get this paperwork uh approved through
council.
>> Thank you. Any further? Please call the
role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> no.
>> Mr. Gunover.
>> Yes.
>> And Mr. Miss Smiley.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third reading of temporary
resolution 3426.
Fails.
>> Failed. No, it fails. We have two
members out and one voted no.
>> That's correct. Okay.
>> Okay. We now move on to temporary
resolution 3526.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to readvertise for bids
and enter into a contract for
construction of the east side
east 6th Avenue bridge over Feder's Run
replacement project and to hire a
consultant to provide construction
inspection services and to declare an
emergency. This through public works
committee, Mr. Carr and Mr. Bisjack.
>> Council member Carr. Um, nothing further
to add to this. Uh, this is the first of
three readings and Mr. Bisjack will be
my second.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 3526.
Temporary resolution 3626.
>> A [clears throat] resolution to
authorize the service safety director to
apply for the Ohio 136
general assembly capital budget
community project and to declare an
emergency. This through finance
committee, Mr. Skunover and Mr. Adles.
Council member Spoonover.
[clears throat]
>> Uh, Mr. President, I'd like to make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third readings
of temporary resolution 3626.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion, a second to suspend
the rules and wave the second and third
readings of temporary resolution 3626.
Any discussion?
>> No. Thank you. Please call the rule.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Cohen,
>> Sorry. Miss H. Mrs. Hoop. Yes,
>> Mr. Nisley.
>> Yes,
>> Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes.
>> And Miss Smiley.
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third reading of temporary
resolution 3626 passes 8 to zero.
Council member Skunover.
>> Yes, Mr. President. I'd like to make a
motion that council pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
resolution 3626.
>> Second.
>> Motion second to pass gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution 3626. Any further discussion?
>> I don't have any.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> And Miss Smiley,
>> Motion to pass and gross and enter upon
the written record. Temporary resolution
3626 passes 8 to zero. Temporary
resolution 3726.
Sorry.
>> A resolution to authorize the service
safety director to submit a fiscal year
2027 community project fundings request
through congress toy balderson and to
declare an emergency. This is through
finance committee Mr. Skunover, Mr. Als.
>> Council member Skunover.
>> Yes, Mr. President. I'd like to make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third readings
of temporary resolution 3726.
>> Second. We have a motion in a second to
suspend the rules and we have the second
third reading of temporary resolution
3726.
Any further discussion on the motion to
suspend?
>> I don't have any.
>> Thank you. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Nisley,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> And Miss Smiley,
>> Motion to suspend the rules. And we have
the second and third reading of
temporary resolution 3726 passes 8 to
zero. Council member Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
resolution 3726.
>> Second.
>> A motion and a second to pass and gross
and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 3726. Any
discussion?
>> Thank you.
>> Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mr. Carr,
>> yes.
>> Miss Cohen,
>> Ms. Hoop.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Nisley.
>> Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Miss Smiley.
>> Temporary resolution 3726 passes 8 to 0.
>> We now move on to the reading of
ordinances. We have no third readings.
We begin with second reading of
temporary ordinance 4-26.
an ordinance authorizing the mayor to
grant four permanent supplemental
easements to the Ohio Power Company
necessary for the construction and
maintenance of electric facilities and
to declared emergency. This is through
law committee, Miss Smiley and Mr. Cart.
>> Council member Smiley.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Second of
three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance 4-26.
We now move on to first reading
beginning with temporary ordinance 5-26.
An ordinance to amend permanent
ordinance 3 or 63-25
the management pay ordinance to add an
assistant prosecutor position for a
limited time period of time and declare
an emergency. This through finance
committee Mr. Skunover and Mr.
Council member Skunover.
>> First of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 5-26.
Temporary ordinance 6-26.
>> An ordinance authorizing the service
safety director to execute a lease
amendment with Park National Bank and to
declare an emergency. This through law
committee, Mr. Carr and Mr. Al.
>> Council member Carr.
>> First of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 6-26.
That concludes the reading of ordinances
this evening.
We have no tabled legislation.
Is there any unfinished business for
council members?
Hearing none, we'll now move to new
business. Um I believe that the liquor
permit that you had mentioned in
correspondence received that we are
waiting to um deal with that um pending
a further review. Is that correct, law
director Hall?
>> Sure. Yes. We'd like some additional
information from law law enforcement
prior to moving forward with that. So,
I'd appreciate it if you all would just
hold on that for the moment.
>> We will hold on that particular um
action. Um we'll now move to updates
from council members through their
committees. We'll begin with council
member Bisjack this evening.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. President. Um well,
there's not really much to update here
from the safety committee because most
of the legislation we talked about in
safety committee has been passed in the
last two meetings. So, at this point, I
have no new updates.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. President.
>> Thank you,
>> Miss Cohen.
>> Um, administrative services, we met in
February. Um, we haven't had much
legislation other than the NOPEC um
energy grant from uh the city. Uh but at
the meeting, Mark Starr introduced his
department, gave an overview of all
their projects and updates um on on
responsibilities and the people everyone
was there. Um I'm not going to go into
all the different responsibilities. The
one I wanted to mention that Dave
Farllo, who's responsible for our fiber
network, was um very excited to discuss
how important our fiber is to not only
the city but also to other organizations
that use our fiber network, which I
thought was really interesting because I
didn't realize that. Um and at the same
time, we discussed how those
organizations compensate the city for
that use. It's not like we give it away
free. Um, the other thing that was
interesting to me, Scott Snyder, the
manager of GIS, talked about his
department, which impacts every city,
every single city department out there.
It's amazing what they do. and he talked
about his drone um that they they
recently bought and the person that runs
it um and how helpful it's been in terms
of helping to identify problems on city
buildings where maybe there was damage
and no one has to climb up there. And
also the um community development
department can more easily work with um
applicants for the roof replacement um
program. It makes it easier for them to
evaluate that. And then finally,
Danielle in HR discussed the success of
the continued success of the medical and
mental um health clinics uh as well as
how well we're doing on our workers comp
that we were re recently highlighted in
an article um released by Sedwick who is
our managed care organization. That's
it.
>> Thank you, Council Member Als.
>> Nothing new to report.
>> Thank you, Council Member Smiley. The
law committee met on February 20th and
we had a special guest with Jennifer
Sitterly who is the Greenfield Township
trustee who came to us with possible
part possible partnership agreements
between the city and the township uh for
not only for just awareness but also
consideration for the buffer zones and
reszoning in the future. But the mayor
did confirm that there was nothing
imminent happening there. We had the law
director's budget updates and staff
updates which we've been working through
with the new prosecutor and hiring
starting in March. The law director
corrected misinformation p public post
posted publicly on social media from an
elected official regarding the violence
against women act funding requirements
which was um informative. And then we
also have this upcoming legislation with
a that we were working through. So, our
next meeting is February 17th at 2 or
12:30 in the Main Street 1897 conference
room. And then I want to take the
opportunity to publicly acknowledge uh
the wonderful public presentation done
by our community development department
on Thursday where they were talking
about the housing assistance program and
they did a great job of explaining what
was available and the fact that they
were able to give resources to those
organizations. It was very informative
and I wanted to thank them for that.
>> That's all. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Council Member Council Member
Skunover.
>> Um, you guys all get to join in the fun
and finance uh every two weeks when
we're here, but I did want to stress um
with everyone so new and even for non
new members, I mean, the the budgets of
every department is a huge undertaking.
You know, last year during
budget time. It was, you know, hey, make
sure that I as your committee chairs,
you're we we want you to be the expert
of your of your committee. So, they
should be the idea. And we we spoke to I
spoke to the SSD and the mayor about
making sure that your department heads
when you're having your committee
meetings that they're bringing their
budget. So, like like you had stated,
Kate, um the law director brought hers.
We went over that. Um, so that way you
there really aren't any surprises. You
know, the year is going to go really
fast. We're already in March, so um,
really I feel like there's always
something new to learn and you know,
when it's coming to finance and we kind
of get together with all this new
legislation, you know that you're going
to be able to to speak to it. Um,
because there's just a lot going on. So,
I commend everybody with their their
updates. I mean, five new people at one
time is uh is you never know what you're
going to get and you know, everybody's
been putting in the work and always
available to to chat for sure.
>> Council member Carr.
>> Well, first of all, I still don't know
what you're going to get from me. So,
anyway, the uh public works last public
works committee meeting was February
20th. Um, I will touch on a just a few
of the highlights from the LDOT
department. Uh, update. The snow removal
from the last major snowstorm. Uh, had
an opportunity to go out on one of those
trucks and spend on that was $93,000
with,090 manh hours, which I'm sure did
not count my four hours and whatever
time Elena or anybody else spent the
truck. Um, there are new snow six new
plows in process of being purchased. Um
budget for that was said was at $16,000.
Um initially the the thought was they
were going to run about $18,000 with an
over 400 day lead time. Um they have now
have those uh purchased with a 180 uh
day lead time. So we'll have them in
time for next year at 14,000 each. So it
cost savings of $2,000 per
[clears throat] per plow. Um,
also have a new appreciation for how
hard it is to uh find people to mow
cemeteries. Um,
so the contract for the Maple Grove and
Forest Rose cemeteries is at 185,000
budgeted at 150. So working to uh
overcome a $35,000 deficit there.
However, also on the cemetery side, the
replacement of their 2008 F550 dump
truck uh that is being transferred to
LDOT um will come in under budget by
$22,000 um at 108. Um
at a high level um some of the
legislation we uh talked about tonight
being the uh Arbor Valley um uh project
and the well the street improvement
program. Those bids are in um u accept
those bids are awarded and and ready to
go and u we have the delay on the uh 6th
Avenue bridge construction with putting
that back out to bid.
>> Thank you for your update. Council
member Nisley
>> and thank you Mr. President. Um the uh
service committee met on February the
12th. Uh we heard from uh from all the
departments, parks, sanitation,
utilities, collection, and uh the gas
department. Um particularly with the gas
with the parks department, we discussed
a variety of issues including an update
to Bowowers Park um and uh and the
Miller Park redevelopment update, which
we uh worked on legislation already in
previous uh councils to address that
phase one of that issue. Um, we also
discussed the possibility of future
legislation that the parks department
may be um pursuing
regarding a uh a maintenance shop. So,
we talked about that. The sanitation
department provided us their revenue and
expense reports. So, that was very
helpful. Um, the utilities collections
office, there's a lot of exciting things
going on with the utilities collections
office in in regards to um as as in
regards to e checkeks, which was I know
was a big thing. a payments of those
autopay payments for your utilities. Um,
and including the uh the brand new
notification system that's been working
out that's been working out very well. I
know I've gotten plenty of updates that
have been very helpful. Um, we also
discussed a variety of different issues
including um renters and multif family
units to see their usage which I think
was very very helpful information. Um,
and then discussion on uh easier
transfer of services from one city
address to another. Um and uh in regards
to the municipal gas department, we
talked about um all the work they have
done over the last year and a half or so
on their on their main replacement
project. Um lots of different stuff they
have done and and it was incredible to
hear about how under budget they came
and and getting all that work done. Um
and we talked about some of the the
volatility in the um the gas costs with
with the super cold snap that we
experienced back in January. Um and uh
and smart the smart meter pilot program
was discussed as well as cost savings
over um private utilities like like uh
Columbia Gas. So overall we had a very
good council meeting and looking forward
to our next one which will be in May. I
don't recall the day but it'll be in
May. Thank you Mr. President.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Thank you Mr. President. Um I chair
economic development and we don't have a
lot of updates. Um, however, I would
suggest if anyone is interested, the
housing study is online on the port
authorities website under live, work,
play, and then you click under live and
you can um check out the housing study
that was done last year. Um, and my next
meeting is April 30th. It's a Thursday
at 7:30 in the morning.
>> Thank you.
>> We'll now move on to the announcement of
scheduled meetings. I have next regular
sessions of council March 23rd, 2026 at
6:30 p.m. here in council chambers and
then April 6, 2026 at 6:30 p.m. in
council chambers. Sir,
>> we have no special scheduled meetings,
regularly scheduled committee meetings.
>> I have four of them for the next coming
month. I have safety committee
April 3rd, 2026 at 8 a.m. in the 1897
conference room in city hall. Water
Pollution Control Committee um April
10th, 2026 at 7:30 a.m. in the 1897
conference room, City Hall. Law
Committee meeting
April 17th, 2026 at 12:30 p.m. in the
1897 conference room, city in city hall.
And then finally, economic development
meeting April 30th, 2026 at 7:30 a.m. in
1897 conference room city hall.
>> Reading of bills. I have one for $65.78
for publication of resolution I'm sorry
ordinance um permanent ordinance 3-26.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to pay the bill.
>> Second.
>> A motion and second to pay the bill. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. We have no
need for an executive session this
evening. I'd entertain a motion to
adjurnn.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make that
motion we adjourn. Second. A motion and
second to adjurnn. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. Please
remember to stay and sign your
legislation this evening. Thank you.
>> [music]